Guide to the Montana Department of Public Instruction. Division of Indian Education Records 1947-1976
Montana Historical Society
Montana Department of Public Instruction. Division of Indian Education Records
1947-1976
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 334
Montana. Department of Public Instruction. Division of Indian Education.
1.5 linear feet of shelf space
The Division of Indian Education was a program within the office of the Superintendent of Public Instruction. Records (1967-1977) include general correspondence; financial records on the dispersal of federal funds; contracts with the federal government; speeches and writings; subject files on related organizations; and miscellany.
The office of Superintendent of Public Instruction was created by the 1872 Montana Territorial Legislative Assembly to replace the older office of school commissioner. The Montana Constitution of 1889 made the office elective and defined its functions. In 1959 the Montana Legislative Assembly created the Department of Public Instruction to administer the office under the direction of the Superintendent of Public Instruction.
The United States Congress passed the Johnson-O'Malley Act in 1934 to provide funding for public school districts on Indian reservations. The payments were in lieu of taxes to compensate for the tax exempt reservation lands. Until 1946 financial arrangements were made between the local Indian agency office and the local school board. In 1946 the Division of Indian Education was established within the Office of Superintendent of Public Instruction to negotiate contracts directly with the U.S. Bureau of Indian Affairs. Gradually BIA schools were abandoned in favor of local school board-controlled schools. Starting in 1964 Public Law 874 regulated most of the funding of reservation schools, and Johnson-O'Malley funds were used primarily to fund special projects. Among the supervisors of Indian Education were Knute W. Bergen, William C. Howard, Earl J. Barlow, Dorrance D. Steele, and Robert W. Parsley. In addition superintendents Mary M. Condon, Harriet E. Miller, and Dolores Colburg handled much of the division's affairs directly. From 1975 to 1977 Bill Yellowtail served as assistant supervisor.
The records consist primarily of general correspondence (1948-1968) arranged chronologically and general correspondence (1973-1976) arranged separately by community and by correspondent. In addition there are financial records (1948-1975) on the dispersal of federal funds; contracts (1947-1962, 1968) with the federal government; speeches and writings; subject files (1957-1975) on related organizations; and miscellany.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Indians of North America--Education--Montana
St. Ignatius (Mont.)
Montana; Native Americans
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence (by correspondent)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Bureau of Indian Affairs, Wesley D'Ewart, Mike Mansfield, et al. re administration of Indian education funds), 1948-1950 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Bureau of Indian Affairs, local school districts, Mike Mansfield, et al. re administration of Indian education funds, school conditions at Chinook, Ronan, Harlem, etc.), 1951-1952 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Bureau of Indian Affairs, local school districts, Mike Mansfield, et al. re administration of Indian education funds, including a controversy over delayed funding in 1954), 1953-1957 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Bureau of Indian Affairs, local school districts, Mike Mansfield, Lee Metcalf, et al. re surplus food commodities, conditions at Browning and Dixon, new school at Rocky Boy, etc.), 1958 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Bureau of Indian Affairs, local school districts, et al. re conditions at Poplar, new school at Rocky Boy, school lunch program, etc.), 1959-1960 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Bureau of Indian Affairs, local school districts, Lee Metcalf, Mike Mansfield, et al. re school at Busby, Public Law 874 entitlement, etc.), 1961-1964 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Bureau of Indian Affairs, local school districts, Lutheran Indian Mission, Miles S. Horn (White Crow) et al. re school at Rocky Boy, Signa Bell, etc.), 1966-1968 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
- General Correspondence (by community)
  - Arlee, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Box Elder and Rocky Boy (includes brief history of Rocky Boy's Reservation), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Brockton (includes "Brockton High School Critical Building Needs Assessment and Recommendations;" "Reality of Dream"; and "Educational Concepts with the New School"), 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Browning and Babb, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Busby, 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Charlo, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Crow Agency, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Cut Bank, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Dixon (includes disciplining of high school basketball player), 1974 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Dodson, 1974 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - East Glacier Park, 1974 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Edgar, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Elmo, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Frazer, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Hardin, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Harlem, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Havre (includes minutes of Johnson-O'Malley Indian Parent Council and Indian Education Committee), 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Hays-Lodge Pole, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Heart Butte (includes "Heart-Butte Reading Program"), 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Hot Springs, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Lame Deer (includes papers presented at Fifth Annual Teachers Workshop, 1973; and material on Follow-through Program cancellation, 1974), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Lodge Grass (includes curriculum), 1974-1976 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Polson, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Poplar, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Pryor (includes "Pryor Public School Board policies" and Johnson-O'Malley funds proposal), 1974-1976 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Ronan (includes controversy over funding of Indian program; and district school census), 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - St. Ignatius, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - St. Xavier, 1974 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - Starr, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - Valier, 1974 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - Wolf Point, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
  - Wyola, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
- General Correspondence (by correspondent)
  - A-F (includes Confederated Salish and Kootenai Tribes; Diane Dabbert re history of Indian education in Montana; and Far West Laboratory re career education curriculum), 1969-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
  - G-K (includes Jessica Schultz Graham re James Willard Schultz Indian Heritage Award; Indian Studies Project; and Herbert S. Kirk re Browning ceramics project), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
  - Mike Mansfield; Lee Metcalf, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 22)
  - M (includes Montana Indian Education Association; and Montana Inter-Tribal Policy Board), 1972-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 23)
  - North American Indian Alliance (re Pride in Indian Heritage Program), 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
  - U.S. Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1968-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 26)
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (includes Office of Indian Education; Division of Bilingual Education; Public Health Service; etc.), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 27)
  - U-W (includes University of Montana; and University of Utah), 1972-1974 (Box-folder 2 / 28)
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 2 / 29)
- Financial Records
  - Budgets under federal contract, 1948-1962, 1975 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Funds distribution, reimbursement, etc., 1948-1958, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
- Legal Documents
  - Contracts with federal government for Indian education, 1947-1962, 1968 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
- Reports
  - Annual reports to U.S. Office of Indian Education, 1948-1950, 1963 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Annual report of Johnson-O'Malley program, 1970, 1975 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Monthly activity reports, 1973 March- 1975 June (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - School visitation reports, 1973-01975 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Untitled report by R.J. Murray, educational field agent (re school financing), 1947 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
- Speeches and Writings
  - Rocky Boy Public School dedication speech by Dolores Colburg, 1947-1973 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
- Subject File
  - American Indian Athletic Hall of Fame, 1973 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
  - Congressional bill for termination of federal supervision of Flathead Reservation (includes Mary Condon testimony), 1954 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
  - Developmental Indian Sports Clinic of the Upper States (DISCUS), 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
  - Indian education reimbursement (includes manual of procedures; and conference with Bureau of Indian Affairs), 1957-1958 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
  - Johnson-O'Malley Act (includes typed copy of bill; memo on program), 1934, undated (Box-folder 3 / 14)
  - Montana Indian Education Conference, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
  - Montana Indian High School Student Debate Tournament, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3 / 16)
  - Montana Indian Youth Practicum, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 3 / 17)
  - Northern Cheyenne Research and Human Development Association, undated (Box-folder 3 / 18)
- Miscellany
  - Address by Dr. Angie Deboe at Governors' Interstate Indian Council meeting, 1957 (Box-folder 3 / 19)
  - "An Appreciation of the Northern Cheyenne Tribe," by Father Marion Roessler, circa 1952 (Box-folder 3 / 20)
  - Notes on Milk River flood damage; statistical data on reservations; etc., 1952, undated (Box-folder 3 / 20)
  - List of public schools served by Johnson-O'Malley funds, 1975 (Box-folder 3 / 21)
  - Nepotism law explanation, 1973 (Box-folder 3 / 22)